<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Blog of Sebastian Häni]]></title><description><![CDATA[A personal blog about things I am interested in.]]></description><link>https://sebastianhaeni.github.com</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 23:39:24 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Dissecting a paper's writing style]]></title><description><![CDATA[In this post I want to dissect a paper’s style and try to criticize it irregardless of it’s content.
The paper is the one mentioned in the…]]></description><link>https://sebastianhaeni.github.com/0004-dissecting-paper-style/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://sebastianhaeni.github.com/0004-dissecting-paper-style/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2020 20:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In this post I want to dissect a paper’s style and try to criticize it irregardless of it’s content.
The paper is the one mentioned in the previous post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 1.2em&quot;&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amstat.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/00031305.2017.1380080&quot;&gt;Sean J. Taylor &amp;#x26; Benjamin Letham (2018) “Forecasting at Scale”, The American Statistician&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Standard Structure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s go over the standard structure of a paper and describe what to look for, and then giving the verdict of how the
paper did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;0. Title&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good title for a paper should honestly reflect the content, give the reader hints what topics it will touch,
and reveals the category of the paper (argumentative, analytical, definition, compare and contrast, cause and effect, report.
interpretive, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes people working for big names put catchy titles on their papers such as “Attention Is
All You Need” or “One Model To Learn Them All”. This yields that if that paper really is groundbreaking, people will
remember it for the catchy name, and it’s easy to talk about it in colloquials. For the authors is a kind of branding
for them as they can afford to add a title like this. A researcher with their feet on the ground probably has to resort
to more bland titles that are humble and serve their purpose in the journal or conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verdict&lt;/strong&gt;: The title of the paper “Forecasting at Scale” is pretty short and does not summarize the techniques or methods
described in the paper and rather focuses on the fact that the paper is practical experiences made since the word “Scale”
is mentioned. So in my opinion it’s a bit catchy but that’s maybe in the nature of the authors since they work for Facebook
and can afford to have a title like that. It’s clear the content will not be about biomedical topics or physics.
It could also be about weather forecasting if it weren’t published in a journal named “The American Statistician”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1. Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The abstract is the first thing a paper, and the part most often read. It should stand for itself and not require the
reader to read any other part of the paper to understand it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The structure of an abstract is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Problem: what is it and why it is interesting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Method: what and how is it accomplished&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Result: what is the new achievement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Importance: what follows after the result&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The abstract is for people that &lt;ins&gt;want&lt;/ins&gt; to read the paper. It is not to be confused by the conclusion which is for
people that &lt;ins&gt;have read&lt;/ins&gt; the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verdict&lt;/strong&gt;: The abstract gives a nice introduction to the field of forecasting time series in the first sentence. It makes me
feel guided into the topic. The second sentence starts explaining the problem as it should mention according to our list
above. From then on the abstract still follows the structure but tends to say “we will describe in this paper” and not
actually giving the reader the result right there in the abstract. It’s nicely rounded off by explaining where these
methods are now productively in place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. Introduction and Related Work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The introduction explains the problem in depth and why it’s interesting and important. It also explains why naive approaches
usually fail and why other people have not solved it before and thus makes the problem hard. It should also introduce
the proposed approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This section should also include related work with a brief overview of the current state of the art with explanations
what is new with respect to previous work. It should be come clear what’s the improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verdict&lt;/strong&gt;: The introduction is in itself structured logically, and the reader can easily follow. It explains what they
mean by “scale”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my opinion the paper’s introduction and the main body diverge a little as the introduction explains scaling problems,
and the main body describes solutions to forecasting problems for the good first part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They don’t talk about why these problems have been solved by others though. They also don’t mention
related work. I could imagine the reason being the other few companies that could encounter scales like Facebook don’t
publish their results as white papers. Though I could also imagine the authors didn’t care much about related research work,
since they were building a practical implementation that matches their company environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3. Main Body&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This part should talk about formulation, implementation, results, experiments, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main body is a longer piece of content which should be grouped into sections. Ideally the text doesn’t introduce
more than one idea per sentence or paragraph. A topic should be in its own section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General good practice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use short words&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use short sentences with simple structure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;keep paragraphs short&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoid buzzwords, clichés and slang&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoid excess, in length or style&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;omit unnecessary material&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;be specific, not vague or abstract&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;break these rules if there is a good reason to do so&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verdict&lt;/strong&gt;: The main body is well-structured, sections are not too long, paragraphs have a reasonable length and contains
a good amount of visualizations. Details as to why they have chosen a certain method over another are often left out
as one can read the reasons in the respective paper, which I guess follows the principle of omitting unnecessary material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4. Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conclusion is a brief summary of the main findings and includes a discussion, perspective and future work etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verdict&lt;/strong&gt;: The conclusion doesn’t go into any details anymore, which is good as it should be brief. What I’m missing from it is
some sort of critical questioning of the results. What the authors describe is only positive and that they are happy.
That’s maybe what truly are. There’s no mention of future work of possible improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;5. Acknowledgements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the name says, in this part the authors acknowledge people that helped the creation of the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;6. References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References should be complete and relevant and correctly cited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;7. Appendices&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This part is optional and sometimes used to append large figures, tables or code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Style Review&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Graphs, Figures and Tables&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t heard about Edward Tufte, go read about his work now. He has produced some great literature about
statistics visualizations. He talks about information design (e.g. data-ink ratio), criticizes PowerPoint, encourages
small multiples (produce many small visualizations instead of one superimposed graph) and other techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than that it should be clear that figures and tables should be easy to read and understand, show relevant data
and have a caption explaining them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verdict&lt;/strong&gt;: The paper has some very good graphs, and some which are not that good. It seems they have been produced
in different styles. Generally I would like the visualizations to have a common style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I take two examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good:&lt;/strong&gt; I like the color coding and the display of the seasonal effects of the weekdays. The main thing here to criticize
is the color choice for Saturday as it’s barely readable. They could also reduce the grey background lines and increase
the data to ink ratio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 548px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/blog/static/9367b79a1c98861d1c41451c843df5c1/a58fe/good-fig.png&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 37.16216216216216%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAAHCAYAAAAIy204AAAACXBIWXMAAAsSAAALEgHS3X78AAABaklEQVQoz32Ra0/bMBiF8///y4TEPjCJi1il0ValKSwbFFogK5c2xGkuTpPUuTx7HcRXjnxs2T4+r33slGVJnu+4W6x48N9YvQQoFROqhFwXwh11ZdhXe4wwS3OmfxfM/RV+GJIXJXGUEGwCLBz1HrKJFD+uJwy8K86F30ZjTqYup9MZZzOPo8mMoXfLxe9bDmRv4F2yjtZs4jfSnaYqDUmSil2HE0VbtonifjFm+XAto8vh8ID5/RTvZiJmxxxdnuDOXX79GfF9fMjT0qXIIzFSQk1eVQThO13b4oShkien1HuFTjdk8SvP/oBk+0ys/vH4NOTFHxGulwSvN/iPPynLlA90NLWhNAWZzuwUp2kaSqlQ1y1109IIjcn7UZoUyug62W+MrO2pKile16IxPSubrdEUhf7I0HZFUfRs5cpWrHXei21JG0ko4VsYU5NlutdYrf1Qe+4TXScZ2u4rGGNvVX2psR6fPv8BGBIRiDt2SAgAAAAASUVORK5CYII=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Good figure showing time series&quot;
        title=&quot;Good figure showing time series&quot;
        src=&quot;/blog/static/9367b79a1c98861d1c41451c843df5c1/a58fe/good-fig.png&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/blog/static/9367b79a1c98861d1c41451c843df5c1/12f09/good-fig.png 148w,
/blog/static/9367b79a1c98861d1c41451c843df5c1/e4a3f/good-fig.png 295w,
/blog/static/9367b79a1c98861d1c41451c843df5c1/a58fe/good-fig.png 548w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 548px) 100vw, 548px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bad:&lt;/strong&gt; This figure looks less optimal. On the first chart I don’t know what the dotted line is or why the other one is blue.
It is also dangerous to put three charts together implying they could be compared even they have different timelines
and should not be compared. Also, isn’t weekly also a trend (referring to the y-axis descriptions).
&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 531px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/blog/static/4985d3207d952e455d5da594f59ce9d3/d4713/bad-fig.png&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 77.70270270270271%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAAQCAYAAAAWGF8bAAAACXBIWXMAAAsSAAALEgHS3X78AAABpklEQVQ4y61Uy47iMBD0/38Rd05IHDjMaoYE0A5kIS9DniR24tS6e5KI56CRxlKpK93ldttxW+CXh1itVlgul3BdF8Qdx2EQJx/FiA+6Z3yYL6IohO/7iKIIUkoEQYgwDPmbQDHyx3HMnGIDJytjOfpJJ4xpH5bedd1D/yu9UFqhaRq0bdvji+tGj/wyppS60hFovtaaudA2YdvcTiSRvvPxQlo99A9FiSHzM8GPE95v+fsK1dOE/ZaNPYvOGHvY5rqSVxXan2MYZqyQuEiKM/JzzQk6+oOdYXSmGTmDYhZtozjRkGQAHR1Z4QYp/sY5ZFEjtvBOJT5lwT7iQVbhVCpklWakdvFK28rurlV/bepzCVVXyIsCpzTDMckgkxTRMUEgE+zCI9b7GM6/COuDxNIL4Vr74UV4t/izDRhvnz5bQS2z3+9RFDnKsmCcR1uisgvWPeIwwGa9QmA7I8tzpFmOJMuQ2EKoGLKccLPZ8IG+Go7V7nY7HA7+88fhsnW+A43ZbIbpdIrJZALP8/pWNFc6cTvptocvY9vtFovFAvP5nB+DR/r/S3/XocnlP1IAAAAASUVORK5CYII=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Bad figure showing component of forecast&quot;
        title=&quot;Bad figure showing component of forecast&quot;
        src=&quot;/blog/static/4985d3207d952e455d5da594f59ce9d3/d4713/bad-fig.png&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/blog/static/4985d3207d952e455d5da594f59ce9d3/12f09/bad-fig.png 148w,
/blog/static/4985d3207d952e455d5da594f59ce9d3/e4a3f/bad-fig.png 295w,
/blog/static/4985d3207d952e455d5da594f59ce9d3/d4713/bad-fig.png 531w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 531px) 100vw, 531px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Justin Zobel (2014) Writing for Computer Science, Third Edition, New York: Springer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Facebook's Prophet and the paper]]></title><description><![CDATA[For the AI seminar, I am attending, I selected the following paper:  Sean J. Taylor & Benjamin Letham (2018) “Forecasting at Scale”, The…]]></description><link>https://sebastianhaeni.github.com/0003-facebook-prophet-paper/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://sebastianhaeni.github.com/0003-facebook-prophet-paper/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;For the AI seminar, I am attending, I selected the following paper:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 1.2em&quot;&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amstat.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/00031305.2017.1380080&quot;&gt;Sean J. Taylor &amp;#x26; Benjamin Letham (2018) “Forecasting at Scale”, The American Statistician&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the coming weeks, I want to evaluate the method described in the paper and see what can be accomplished with it in an
environment relevant to me. The relevant environment for me is time series, mostly business time series, but can be of
different sorts as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Content&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper “Forecasting at scale” describes the method that Facebook uses to do forecasting on time series data based
on an additive model where non-linear trends are fit with yearly, weekly and daily seasonality, plus holiday effects.
The procedure is robust to missing data and shifts in the trend, and typically handles outliers well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Motivation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m explaining my motivation behind selecting the paper:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why have I chosen this paper?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year I got a task when doing volunteering service for the country, to work on a time series data set. I built a
proof of concept system that could process the gigabytes of CSV files and aggregate the time series to different sample
durations. The time series were also transformed using different methods such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CUSUM&quot;&gt;CUSUM&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EWMA_chart&quot;&gt;EWMA&lt;/a&gt; to make them easier to interpret.
I visualized them with &lt;a href=&quot;https://grafana.com/&quot;&gt;Grafana&lt;/a&gt; that I connected to a self-written Python backend using &lt;a href=&quot;https://palletsprojects.com/p/flask/&quot;&gt;Flask&lt;/a&gt;.
The processing of the data was limited to my dev machine and I was restricted from using any other infrastructure. Because
it became clear that single-thread processing would not finish the processing within days, I had to parallelize it with
&lt;a href=&quot;https://dask.org/&quot;&gt;Dask&lt;/a&gt;, which shortened the processing time dramatically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After visualizing the immense amount of data it became clear that we will find some seasonality and trend in subsets
of the time series. Thus I had the idea to decompose the filtered subsets into seasonality and trend. This gave the
opportunity to then create a prediction interval that can be used to find anomalies in the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a quick and dirty implementation, it became clear that producing nice graphs could turn out to be tricky. A
colleague stumbled upon the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/anomalize/index.html&quot;&gt;anomalize&lt;/a&gt; package in R.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 450px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/blog/static/7bad9e4efed277e9b67a873875c8eef7/fc2a6/anomalize.png&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 53.37837837837838%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAALCAYAAAB/Ca1DAAAACXBIWXMAAAsSAAALEgHS3X78AAACDUlEQVQoz3VSa08aURDl/3/vQwu4gYKhIKC2vFRqhfRD/UBcFmhjiWDKsqvysLz2dfd05i5QadKbTDJ3HueeO3NCwvfhuh48T6zN+48FOZd9x4FwXQgfEELAJ38xm2NlWQhZtg2fQHcMf8/LOPwg41OP/fgIdz6HRzGj30dbVWETsdBiucS/hxlYFGc2zGAbp9jzZAKt3cbn8yq0RgPtVguFUgWVi0t4VBviQptenFChYQzR6/Wg3tzg+ts1mpqGn7e30PUBTNOA2mzitFBCJpvH4YcjJMhymSze7oVRq9cDQGYxHA5Rp0Dl7Bz5k4/I5k+QTGUQS6ZkY7FUxlWthtzxKcIHcUSVONLpDJTYe8QTSeTzx+h0OvSjNcPO9x94tRfB6/0oWQT7EUUWR5SYbObcm3cHUOIJZHM5+fBV/SuqF1WcEeOG2sR4MoVNo5KAqqohHFVwRF/5VCiizA21OqqXX1AolpEjxqk0M63QtzX8GuiYPk/xYJrQaSE8b9+xwQsOsWxMXUeL5ta/v8dgMMDo6Qnj8Xg9VwN3NNdutwuDcktqFiJYljSSik8mRiNYzNCXOnQxm81gUYL9rfZEoD1eWgAkdqS0IyvypQ5t28FsvtgKe75YYrWyJJBD4L9JsCx8rBs2d85zLZsUPNXKGTIgN25eWxKYEMHrzNBhTRJDbuQ6vm+OZdkS7OX5A/UzKK+UCXdrAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;anomalize graph&quot;
        title=&quot;anomalize graph&quot;
        src=&quot;/blog/static/7bad9e4efed277e9b67a873875c8eef7/fc2a6/anomalize.png&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/blog/static/7bad9e4efed277e9b67a873875c8eef7/12f09/anomalize.png 148w,
/blog/static/7bad9e4efed277e9b67a873875c8eef7/e4a3f/anomalize.png 295w,
/blog/static/7bad9e4efed277e9b67a873875c8eef7/fc2a6/anomalize.png 450w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 450px) 100vw, 450px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We tried it out but concluded that special holidays, weekends and so on still were a problem for anomalize which uses
STL (Seasonality and Trend decomposition using LOESS, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scb.se/contentassets/ca21efb41fee47d293bbee5bf7be7fb3/stl-a-seasonal-trend-decomposition-procedure-based-on-loess.pdf&quot;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;)
and methods from Twitter’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/twitter/AnomalyDetection&quot;&gt;AnomalyDetection&lt;/a&gt; library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So our research continues and we found the library &lt;a href=&quot;https://facebook.github.io/prophet/&quot;&gt;Prophet&lt;/a&gt; which looked promising,
as it’s method promises that it can not only cope with holiday effects but also work at scale, has automatic changepoint
detection and allows for Analyst-in-the-Loop Modeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But unfortunately the time we had run out and I had no chance to look at this method in depth. This AI seminar now gives
me the chance to catch up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why is it relevant and interesting?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook has developed the Prophet library in house and is sharing it as open source with the community. At my day job,
we’re operating applications at scale and thus are confronted with the same problems that Facebook has tried to solve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it can be interesting for larger companies trying to achieve application operating models that can do self-healing,
scale automatically using predictions, anticipate surges and find anomalies so an operator can have a closer look and
feed the result back into the model. Until 2025 we want to have AIOps established in the company. And we’re certainly
not the only company trying to do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Expectations &amp;#x26; Goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal of working through this paper and the accompanying library is to deepen my knowledge of how time series analysis
can be approached beside the methods I already know like STL. Also, I would like to be able to tell our business owners
and fellow coworkers if this method could be a useful tool.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[AI Seminar Intro]]></title><description><![CDATA[As mentioned in my first blog post New Beginnings, I’m inscribed to a course
named “AI Seminar”. In this course, each student is expected to…]]></description><link>https://sebastianhaeni.github.com/0002-ai-seminar-intro/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://sebastianhaeni.github.com/0002-ai-seminar-intro/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2020 12:30:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in my first blog post &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/0001-new-beginnings&quot;&gt;New Beginnings&lt;/a&gt;, I’m inscribed to a course
named “AI Seminar”. In this course, each student is expected to read a paper of their choice.
We will go through understanding writing style, understanding content, reviewing and criticizing
a paper, evaluating yourself oneself and have a final presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why I have chosen this seminar&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have not touched on that many results of scientific work. This course is ideal to fix that for me.
We will discuss in person and work through a paper in depth. I feel like this is something that will
always be handy to have experienced regarding my future career, even if I would never write a paper.
But since I’m inscribed in this seminar, I may even would feel comfortable writing a paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That the papers we read are supposed to be in the field of AI is also something adding to my
motivation to choose this seminar as my specialization is Data Science. Meaning I can learn about
some AI methods that I am interested in anyway. So, two flies with one clap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My learning goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My learning goals pretty much align with the course description. So I want to learn about scientific
writing, what a good paper is about and get familiar with a topic of my interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; in detail how the process of writing scientific papers is like and hear from an
expert that has experience in this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to &lt;em&gt;try&lt;/em&gt; criticizing a paper and get feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to &lt;em&gt;refine&lt;/em&gt; my writing skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to &lt;em&gt;get to know&lt;/em&gt; the method explained in my chosen paper in detail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to &lt;em&gt;establish&lt;/em&gt; a regular blogging habit beyond this seminar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to &lt;em&gt;share&lt;/em&gt; my learning process and gain insights how others do doing the same.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[New Beginnings]]></title><description><![CDATA[Why am I starting my own blog? This post is the first ever post in a personal blog.
I try to explain why having a personal blog is a good…]]></description><link>https://sebastianhaeni.github.com/0001-new-beginnings/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://sebastianhaeni.github.com/0001-new-beginnings/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 22:40:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Why am I starting my own blog? This post is the first ever post in a personal blog.
I try to explain why having a personal blog is a good idea IMHO and what gives me the motivation to
start it now. If you don’t have your own place to write, this maybe gives you some motivation to do
so too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Who am I&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m a software engineer working at a large telecommunications company in Switzerland. Here I build
large scale full stack web applications with technologies such as Springboot and Angular. We pursue
a modern development pipeline with state of the art tooling and automation with autonomous releasing
and advanced monitoring techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides that, I’m doing my Master of Science with specialization in Data Science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I have lots of things I learn daily. Some things are personal ideas, some things are
implementations of ideas of the industry, some things are just personal reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Motivation #1: Writing down what I learned&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you learn new things on a daily basis, you will eventually have learned that many relevant things
you are not able to recall each and every learning correctly unless you write it down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if you write it down for your personal use only, you can write down pretty much anything. It
could be confidential, it could be targeting people. This may work very well for you. But if there
is a greater learning, and you stay on the detail level about the problem, you may not be able to
generalize the learning to new problems and you have not thought enough about it to abstract the
problem and solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you write a blog that can be accesses publicly, you need to remove any confidential information
from it. What is left at that point is an abstract description of problem and solution that in
theory should be applicable to you in the future in a new setting. Because you’ll not always be
in the same environment forever and your problem and solution space changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also while you have go through the abstraction process you start to get to the core of you learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Motivation #2: Sharing with others&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might learn useful things that you share verbally, by email or text message, but with a blog you
can share what you learned with people you don’t know. They would probably reach a single article of
the blog through a Google search, read it and apply it to their problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is different to Stackoverflow or GitHub issues that you write about a problem you had with
your own motivation. You’re not solving somebodies problem that they posted and want an answer for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also think that the blog post would be more of a guide to a larger problem with an introduction
and conclusion, several sections and references. It often is not just a few sentences and a code
snippet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By sharing the blog post publicly and including a discussion or comment section, you are able to
get feedback. This may be that you explained something not clearly or that there are other people
that have thought about this problem before that you don’t know about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Motivation #3: Refine my writing skills&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Explaining something so everybody can understand is an essential skill for engineers working in
teams. If you want to introduce a new concept, raise awareness about architectural problems and so
on, not everybody will understand what you mean without investing time explaining it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By writing a blog, you are forced to explain complex settings in a clear way. I think the only real
way to get better at this, is to exercise it. So a blog can be an excellent tool to refine your
writing skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also my mother tongue is not English, so this blog allows me to refine my English writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Motivation #4: Trying Gatsby.js&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m reading a lot of people are using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gatsbyjs.org/&quot;&gt;Gatsby.js&lt;/a&gt;. It sounds like a promising
technology and I am eager to get my hands on it. It has some cool concepts. So, I’m building this
blog with Gatsby.js.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sebastianhaeni/blog&quot;&gt;https://github.com/sebastianhaeni/blog&lt;/a&gt;
if you want to read the source code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Motivation #5: AI Seminar course&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, and where I finally got the motivation to start this blog is a seminar about AI that I’m
inscribed in for my Masters. In that course, we go through a scientific paper and are expected to
write blog posts about the process and what we learned when reading and asking questions about it.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>